<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 file:/D:/gdrive/PERSONAL/Masters/Dissertation/akn-core-v1.0-csprd01/part2-specs/schemas/akomantoso30.xsd">
    <act name="act">
        <meta>

            <identification source="#indiacode">
                <FRBRWork>
                    <FRBRthis value="/akn/in/act/1963-05-10/1963-19/main"/>
                    <FRBRuri value="/akn/in/act/1963-05-10/1963-19"/>
                    <FRBRdate date="1963-05-10" name="Generation"/>
                    <FRBRauthor href="#ashok" as="#author"/>
                    <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
                    <FRBRnumber value="1963-19"/>
                </FRBRWork>
                <FRBRExpression>
                    <FRBRthis value="/akn/in/act/1963-05-10/1963-19/eng@1986-05-15/main"/>
                    <FRBRuri value="/akn/in/act/1963-05-10/1963-19/eng@1986-05-15"/>
                    <FRBRdate date="1986-05-15" name="Generation"/>
                    <FRBRauthor href="#ashok" as="#editor"/>
                    <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
                </FRBRExpression>
                <FRBRManifestation>
                    <FRBRthis value="/akn/in/act/1963-05-10/1963-19/eng@1986-05-15/main.xml"/>
                    <FRBRuri value="/akn/in/act/1963-05-10/1963-19/eng@1986-05-15.akn"/>
                    <FRBRdate date="1986-05-15" name="Generation"/>
                    <FRBRauthor href="#ashok" as="#editor"/>
                    <FRBRformat value="xml"/>
                </FRBRManifestation>
            </identification>

            <publication date="1986-05-15" showAs="Official Languages Act" name="officialLanguagesAct" number="1963-19"/>

            <lifecycle source="#ashok">
                <eventRef eId="event_1" date="1963-05-10" source="#ro1" type="generation"/>
                <eventRef eId="event_2" date="1986-05-15" source="#ro1" type="amendment"/>
                <eventRef eId="event_3" date="1963-01-10" source="#ro1" type="generation"/>
                <eventRef eId="event_4" date="1969-05-19" source="#ro1" type="generation"/>
                <eventRef eId="event_5" date="1970-03-07" source="#ro1" type="generation"/>
            </lifecycle>
            <analysis source="#parliament">
                
                <passiveModifications>
                    
                    <efficacyMod eId="efmod_2" type="entryIntoEfficacy" period="#period_2">
                        <source href="#sec_5__sse_1"/>
                        <destination href="#sec_5__sse_1"/>
                    </efficacyMod>
                    
                    <efficacyMod eId="efmod_1" type="entryIntoEfficacy" period="#period_3">
                        <source href="#sec_6"/>
                        <destination href="#sec_6"/>
                    </efficacyMod>
                    
                                        
                    <efficacyMod eId="efmod_3" type="entryIntoEfficacy" period="#period_4">
                        <source href="#sec_7"/>
                        <destination href="#sec_7"/>
                    </efficacyMod>
                    

                    
                    <textualMod type="substitution" eId="mod_1">
                        <source href="/akn/in/act/1968-01-01/1968-1/eng@/main#sec_2"/>
                        <destination href="#sec_3"/>

                    </textualMod>
                    <textualMod type="insertion" eId="mod_2">
                        <source href="/akn/in/act/1968-01-01/1968-1/eng@/main#sec_3"/>
                        <destination href="#sec_4__sse_4__mod_2"/>

                    </textualMod>

                    <textualMod type="substitution" eId="mod_4" period="#period_1">
                        <source href="/akn/in/act/1986-01-01/1986-4/eng@/main#sec_2"/>
                        <destination href="#sec_8__sse_2__mod_4"/>
                    </textualMod>

                </passiveModifications>
            </analysis>

            <temporalData source="#parliament">
                <temporalGroup>
                    <timeInterval eId="period_1" refersTo="#mod_4" start="#event_2"/>
                    <timeInterval eId="period_2" refersTo="#efmod_1" start="#event_3"/>
                    <timeInterval eId="period_3" refersTo="#efmod_2" start="#event_4"/>
                    <timeInterval eId="period_4" refersTo="#efmod_3" start="#event_5"/>
                </temporalGroup>
            </temporalData>


            <references source="#parliament">
                <original eId="ro1" href="/akn/in/act/1963-05-10/1963-19/eng@/main" showAs="Original"/>
            </references>
            
            <notes source="#editors-office">
                <note eId="mod_note_2">
                    <p>Subs. by Act 1 of 1968, s. 2, for s. 3.</p>
                </note>
                 <note eId="mod_note_3">
                    <p>Ins. by Act 1 of 1968, s. 3.</p>
                </note>
                
                <note eId="mod_note_4">
                    <p>Subs. by Act 4 of 1986, s. 2 and sch. (w.e.f. 15.5.1986).</p>
                </note>
            </notes>
        </meta>
        <preface>
            <p>
                <docTitle refersTo="#shortTitle">THE OFFICIAL LANGUAGES ACT, 1963</docTitle>
            </p>
            <p>
                <docNumber refersTo="#currentAct">ACT NO. 19 OF 1963</docNumber>
            </p>
            <p> <docDate date="1963-05-10">10th May, 1963</docDate> </p>
        </preface>
        <preamble>
            <p>
                <docTitle refersTo="#longTitle">An Act to provide for the languages which may be
                    used for the official purposes of the Union, for transaction of business in
                    Parliament, for Central and State Acts and for certain purposes in High
                    Courts.</docTitle>
            </p>
            <p> BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fourteenth Year of the Republic of India as
                follows:--</p>

        </preamble>
        <body>

            <section eId="sec_1">
                <num> 1. </num>
                <heading>Short title and commencement. </heading>
                <subsection eId="sec_1__sse_1">
                    <paragraph eId="sec_1__sse_1__para_1">
                        <num>(1)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p>This Act may be called the Official Languages Act, 1963.</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>
                    <paragraph eId="sec_1__sse_1__para_2">
                        <num>(2)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p>Section 3 shall come into force on the 26th day of January, 1965 and
                                the remaining provisions of this Act shall come into force on such
                                date as the Central Government may, by notification in the
                                Official Gazette, appoint and different dates may be appointed for
                                different provisions of this Act.</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>
                </subsection>
            </section>

            <section eId="sec_2">
                    <num>2. </num>
                    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
                <intro>
                    <p>In this Act, unless the context otherwise
                        requires,--</p>
                </intro>
                <subsection eId="sec_2__sse_1">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>"appointed day", in relation to section 3, means the 26th day of January,
                            1965 and in relation to any other provision of this Act, means the day
                            on which that provision comes into force;</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_2__sse_2">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>"Hindi" means Hindi in Devanagari script.</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
            </section>

            <section eId="sec_3" class="substitution">
                <num>
                    <noteRef href="#mod_note_2" marker="2" placement="bottom"/>3.</num>
                <heading>Continuance of English language for official purposes of the Union and for
                    use in Parliament.</heading>
                <subsection eId="sec_3__sse_1">
                    <num>(1) </num>
                    <intro>
                        <p>Notwithstanding the expiration of the period of fifteen years from the
                            commencement of the Constitution, the English language may, as from the
                            appointed day, continue to be used, in addition to Hindi,--</p>
                    </intro>
                    <paragraph eId="sec_3__sse_1__para_1">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p>for all the official purposes of the Union for which it was being
                                used immediately before that day; and</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>
                    <paragraph eId="sec_3__sse_1__para_2">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p>for the transaction of business in Parliament:</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>
                    <wrapUp eId="sec_3__sse_1__wrapup">
                        <p> Provided that the English language shall be used for purposes of
                            communication between the Union and a State which has not adopted Hindi
                            as its official language:</p>
                        <p> Provided further that where Hindi is used for purposes of communication
                            between one State which has adopted Hindi as its official language and
                            another State which has not adopted Hindi as its official language, such
                            communication in Hindi shall be accompanied by a translation of the same
                            in the English language: </p>
                        <p> Provided also that nothing in this sub-section shall be construed as
                            preventing a State which has not adopted Hindi as its official language
                            from using Hindi for purposes of communication with the Union or with a
                            State which has adopted Hindi as its official language, or by agreement
                            with any other State, and in such a case, it shall not be obligatory to
                            use the English language for purposes of communication with that
                            State.</p>
                    </wrapUp>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_3__sse_2">
                    <num>(2)</num>
                    <intro>
                        <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where Hindi or the
                            English language is used for purposes of communication--</p>
                    </intro>

                    <paragraph eId="sec_3__sse_2__para_1">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p>between one Ministry or Department or office of the Central
                                Government and another;</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>


                    <paragraph eId="sec_3__sse_2__para_2">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p>between one Ministry or Department or office of the Central
                                Government and any corporation or company owned or controlled by the
                                Central Government or any office thereof;</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>


                    <paragraph eId="sec_3__sse_2__para_3">
                        <num>(iii)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p> between any corporation or company owned or controlled by the
                                Central Government or any office therof and another, a translation
                                of such communication in the English language or, as the case may
                                be, in Hindi shall also be provided till such date as the staff of
                                the concerned Ministry, Department, Office or Corporation or company
                                aforesaid have acquired a working knowledge of Hindi.</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>

                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_3__sse_3">
                    <num>(3)</num>
                    <intro>
                        <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in <ref href="#sec_3__sse_1">sub-section (1)</ref>, both Hindi and the
                            English language shall be used for--</p>
                    </intro>
                    <paragraph eId="sec_3__sse_3__para_1">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p>resolutions, general orders, rules, notifications, administrative or
                                other reports or press communiques issued or made by the Central
                                Government or by a Ministry, Department or office thereof or by a
                                corporation or company owned or controlled by the Central Government
                                or by any office of such corporation or company;</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>
                    <paragraph eId="sec_3__sse_3__para_2">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p>administrative and other reports and official papers laid before a
                                House or the Houses of Parliament;</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>
                    <paragraph eId="sec_3__sse_3__para_3">
                        <num>(iii) </num>
                        <content>
                            <p>contracts and agreements executed, and licences, permits, notices and
                                forms of tender issued, by or on behalf of the Central Government or
                                any Ministry, Department or office thereof or by a corporation or
                                company owned or controlled by the Central Government or by any
                                office of such corporation or company.</p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_3__sse_4">
                    <num>(4)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1) or sub-section (2)
                            or sub-section (3), the Central Government may, by rules made under
                            section 8, provide for the language or languages to be used for the
                            official purpose of the Union, including the working of any Ministry,
                            Department, section or office, and in making such rules, due
                            consideration shall be given to the quick and efficient disposal of the
                            official business and the interests of the general public and in
                            particular, the rules so made shall ensure that persons serving in
                            connection with the affairs of the Union and having proficiency either
                            in Hindi or in the English language may function effectively and that
                            they are not placed at a disadvantage on the ground that they do not
                            have proficiency in both the languages.</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_3__sse_5">
                    <num>(5)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>The provisions of clause (a) of sub-section (1), and the provisions of
                            sub-section (2), sub-section (3) and sub-section (4) shall remain in
                            force until resolutions for the discontinuance of the use of the English
                            language for the purposes mentioned therein have been passed by the
                            Legislatures of all the States which have not adopted Hindi as their
                            official language and until after considering the resolutions aforesaid,
                            a resolution for such discontinuance has been passed by each House of
                            Parliament.</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
            </section>

            <section eId="sec_4">
                <num> 4.</num>
                <heading> Committee on Official Language.</heading>
                <subsection eId="sec_4__sse_1">
                    <num>(1)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>After the expiration of ten years from the date on which section 3 comes
                            into force, there shall be constituted a Committee on Official Language,
                            on a resolution to that effect being moved in either House of Parliament
                            with the previous sanction of the President and passed by both
                            Houses.</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_4__sse_2">
                    <num>(2)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>The Committee shall consist of thirty members, of whom twenty shall be
                            members of the House of the People and ten shall be members of the
                            Council of States, to be elected, respectively by the members of the
                            House of the People and the members of the Council of States in
                            accordance with the system of proportional representation by means of
                            the single transferable vote.</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_4__sse_3">
                    <num>(3)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>It shall be the duty of the Committee to review the progress made in the
                            use of Hindi for the official purposes of the Union and submit a report
                            to the President making recommendations thereon and the President shall
                            cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament, and sent to
                            all the State Governments.</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_4__sse_4">
                    <num>(4)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>The President may, after consideration of the report referred to in
                            sub-section (3), and the views, if any, expressed by the State
                            Governments thereon, issue directions in accordance with the whole or
                            any part of that report:</p>
                        <p>
                            <noteRef href="#mod_note_3" marker="1"/>
                            <span class="insertion" eId="sec_4__sse_4__mod_2">Provided that the
                                directions so issued shall not be inconsistent with the provisions
                                of section 3.</span>
                        </p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
            </section>
            <section eId="sec_5">

                <num> 5.</num>
                <heading>Authorised Hindi translation of Central Acts, etc. </heading>
                <subsection eId="sec_5__sse_1">
                    <!-- S. 5(1)  comes into force on the 10th January, 1965, vide Notifn.
 No. S.O.  94, dated  the 4th  January, 1965, Gazette of India, Pt. II,
 Sec. 3(ii),  p. 128; -->
                    <num>(1)</num>
                    <intro>
                        <p>A translation in Hindi published under the authority of the President in
                            the Official Gazette on and after the appointed day,--</p>
                    </intro>
                    <paragraph>
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p> of any Central Act or of any Ordinance promulgated by the President,
                                or </p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>
                    <paragraph>
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <content>
                            <p> of any order, rule, regulation or bye-law issued under the
                                Constitution or under any Central Act, shall be deemed to be the
                                authoritative text thereof in Hindi. </p>
                        </content>
                    </paragraph>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_5__sse_2">
                    <num>(2)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>As from the appointed day, the authoritative text in the English language
                            of all Bills to be introduced or amendments thereto to be moved in
                            either House of Parliament shall be accompanied by a translation of the
                            same in Hindi authorised in such manner as may be prescribed by rules
                            made under this Act.</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
            </section>
            <section eId="sec_6">
                <num> 6.</num>
                <heading>Authorised Hindi translation of State Acts in certain cases.</heading>
                <content>
                    <p> Where the Legislature of a State has prescribed any language other than
                        Hindi for use in Acts passed by the Legislature of the State or in
                        Ordinances promulgated by the Governor of the State, a translation of the
                        same in Hindi, in addition to a translation thereof in the English language
                        as required by clause (3) of article 348 of the Constitution, may be
                        published on or after the appointed day under the authority of the Governor
                        of the State in the Official Gazette of that State and in such a case, the
                        translation in Hindi of any such Act or Ordinance shall be deemed to be the
                        authoritative text thereof in the Hindi language.</p>
                </content>
            </section>

            <section eId="sec_7">

                <num>7.</num>
                <heading>Optional use of Hindi or other official language in judgments, etc., of
                    High Courts.</heading>
                <content>
                    <p>As from the appointed day or any day thereafter, the Governor of a State may,
                        with the previous consent of the President, authorise the use of Hindi or
                        the official language of the State, in addition to the English language, for
                        the purposes of any judgment, decree or order passed or made by the High
                        Court for that State and where any judgment, decree or order is passed or
                        made in any such language (other than the English language), it shall be
                        accompanied by a translation of the same in the English language issued
                        under the authority of the High Court.</p>
                </content>
            </section>
            <section eId="sec_8">

                <num> 8. </num>
                <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
                <subsection eId="sec_8__sse_1"> 
                    <num>(1)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make
                            rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection eId="sec_8__sse_2">
                    <num>(2)</num>
                    <content>
                        <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after
                            it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a
                            total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or
                            <noteRef href="#mod_note_4" marker="1" placement="bottom"/>
                            <span class="substitution" eId="sec_8__sse_2__mod_4"> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the
                            session immediately following the session or the successive sessions
                            aforesaid</span> both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or
                            both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall
                            thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as
                            the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment
                            shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done
                            under that rule.</p>
                    </content>
                </subsection>
            </section>
            <section eId="sec_9">
                <num>9. </num>
                <heading>Certain provisions not to apply to Jammu and Kashmir.</heading>
                <content>
                      <p>The provisions of <ref href="#sec_6">section 6</ref> and <ref href="#sec_7">section 7</ref> shall not apply to the State of Jammu
                        and Kashmir.</p>
                </content>
            </section>
        </body>
    </act>
</akomaNtoso>